<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/kipling/kipling-jp3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
			<journal-id>23423</journal-id>
			<journal-title-group>
					<journal-title>test journal</journal-title>
				</journal-title-group>
			
			
		</journal-meta>
		<article-meta>
			
			
			<title-group>
				<article-title><bold>Hickey v Marks</bold></article-title>
				<subtitle><bold>Case report of Hickey v Marks</bold></subtitle>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib>
						<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://testacademicarticle.wordpress.com">http://testacademicarticle.wordpress.com</ext-link>
				</contrib>
		</contrib-group>
			
				<pub-date pub-type="ppub">
					<day>20</day>
					<month>12</month>
					<year>2011</year>
				</pub-date>			
			
			
		</article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
<sec>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The widely publicised libel action brought by the US medical devices company against Dr Wilmhurst has renewed the calls for reform of English libel law. Libel law has come to be seen as a tool of large corporations seeking to silence critics, however well-founded their criticisms. There are also documented - though perhaps less publicised - examples of scientists and even doctors using libel law to silence critics. Hickey v Marks<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="1">1</xref>concerns a General Practitioner who prescribed Diconal (a strong opioid analgesic) to a patient suffering from a drug addiction, who later died from an overdose. His management of this specific case, as well as his adoption of an unorthodox practising style, was questioned by another doctor ( Dr Marks, former chairman of the BMA) in a BBC documentary</p>
<title><bold>The consultation</bold></title>

<fig><label>Figure 1</label><caption><para>Caption text for a figure</para></caption>
<media xlink:href="http://testacademicarticle.files.wordpress.com/2011/12/business-associations-75.png"><alt-text></alt-text><long-desc></long-desc><permissions><copyright-statement></copyright-statement><copyright-holder></copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p></license-p></license></permissions></media></fig>

<p>In 1987 Dr Hickey was a GP in Cornwall. In addition to his regular duties he had adopted alternative and holistic approaches into his medical practice, including in relation to the treatment of drug addicts. The relevant patient, Scholes, approached the practice in an excitable state, claiming to have taken large quantities of Methadrine. He also admitted that he had previously been addicted to heroin and diconal, but that he had been drug-free for four years.</p>
<p>Although Scholes was already a patient of Dr Hickey, on the day of the appointment his notes could not be found, and so no documented medical history was available. Dr Hickey did not take the patient's history, and despite only having four drug addicts on his practice records, he did not seek professional advice for Scholes' management. Dr Hickey then went on to propose a management plan which involved 'dream therapy and going to church.'</p>
<p>From the scant details Dr Hickey gleaned from the patient, and despite a failure to examine him, Dr Hickey concluded that Scholes was suffering from severe Methedrine withdrawal. He prescribed diconal, benzodiazepines and vitamin pills - although at the time he made no record of the specific drugs prescribed. Multiple further prescriptions were provided when Scholes returned to the surgery claiming to have lost the previous prescriptions. On the 17th September 1987, one week after Schules had first presented with symptoms, he was found dead at his home - the cause of death was recorded as drug overdose, and toxic levels of Diconal were found in his bloodstream.</p>
<title>Allegations of incompetence</title>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="2">2</xref>
<p>Seven years after Scholes' death, Dr Mark was involved in the making of a BBC documentary about the events leading up to Scholes' overdose. Among Dr Mark's claims were that Dr Hickey 'was using dangerous, potentially lethal drugs with no idea how to handle them' and that 'he put ideas which are unorthodox ahead of the hard facts that drugs are dangerous.' He criticised Dr Hickey's failure to take a formal history, perform even a basic physical examination, or request specialist psychiatric help. Furthermore he claimed that Diconal should not be used to treat amphetamine addiction, on the grounds that patients will more often than not become Diconal addicts instead</p>
<p><fig><label>Figure 1</label><caption><para>Caption text for a figure</para></caption>
<media xlink:href="http://testacademicarticle.files.wordpress.com/2011/12/business-associations-75.png"><alt-text></alt-text><long-desc></long-desc><permissions><copyright-statement></copyright-statement><copyright-holder></copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons"><license-p></license-p></license></permissions></media></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec>
</sec>

	</body>

	<back>


			<ref-list>
				<title>References</title>
			<ref id="1">
				<label>1</label>
				<mixed-citation>London Artists v Littler	[1969] 2 Q.B. 375; [1969] 2 W.L.R. 409; [1969] 2 All E.R. 193 CA (CivilDivision)
					
						<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2342323</pub-id>
				</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="2">
				<label>1</label>
				<mixed-citation>London Artists v Littler	[1969] 2 Q.B. 375; [1969] 2 W.L.R. 409; [1969] 2 All E.R. 193 CA (CivilDivision)
					
						<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2342323</pub-id>
				</mixed-citation>
			</ref>
		</ref-list>
	</back>

</article>
